Order
The special sitting of the Federal Court
of Appeal is now open
the Honourable Justice Gauthier, The Honorable
Mr. Justice Webb, and the Honourable Madam Justice Rivoalen are presiding.
The court calls file numbers
A-101-18 and A-102-18.
Radu Hociung and the Minister of Public
Safety and Emergency Preparedness.
The Appellant will be representing himself
and Mr. Peterson will be representing the Respondent.
I think I saw you in the room yesterday,
so you know how we proceed.
It's your appeal, and you can rest assured that
we have read the material,
so you can start your representations
Good morning.
First a question: What is the meaning of "appeal"?
Is a request for the court to consider a decision of
a lower court or another authority in decision-making capacity.
Is that about correct?
in this particular case, yesterday it was...
Now this is a motion, okay, and on a motion from a
trial court, we apply the standard of review that
means how we judge whether we can intervene for an
error or not, according to a case called Housen.
If it is a question of law, we apply the
correctness... we see if it's correct.
And if it is mixed fact and law or thing or things
like that, which normally is
a question of summary judgment is normally
mix fact and law, maybe not in this case.
It's palpable and overriding error, and
that's a very high standard
we have to be convinced there was
no record, no evidence whatsoever to ground
the finding of the Federal Court
Of course. My question
okay with you understand it like that
My question was more general, somewhat more
general. It was directed to the word appeal
not necessarily in this court. Because it is
referred, for example in the Federal Court...
the case before us has to do with the Customs Act,
where there's a word there that says a decision of
the Minister may be appealed in the Federal Court.
Yes, but you have to be careful.
What one understands of the word
"appeal" in a statute
does not always mean the same thing.
The Supreme Court told us that in several statutes
the word "appeal" means almost a judicial review,
so it's like
It's a bit complicated. But in this case why is
relevant to your case because what is before us
Is the decision of Justice Gleeson
Yes, the decision of Justice Gleeson
was requested
No, don't worry. I mean this is
be relaxed.
the first instance started as an appeal of
a decision of the minister of Public Safety
section 135. The language in the Customs Act was
that the decision is appealed to the Federal
Court. So my question is what does the word
"appeal" mean in such a setting? does it not mean
I'm requesting the court to have a look
at The Minister's decision?
Yes.
But I'm not sure that this is really
all that relevant to what is before us
It will be.
Okay. So you explain that to us.
Second question is
in the context of the Federal Court,
what is an Act of Parliament?
My understanding is that it is...
That is... it's not a procedural.
It's not a procedural rule.
It is a piece of evidence. It's evidence of the
truth against which the court measures
An Act of Parliament is a statute or a regulation
Um,
that's an Act of Parliament
it is... that's correct. But what is it to you?
Is it evidence? Is it rules? Is it procedural?
It's law.
It's the law.
it's the measuring stick.
Yes.
so an Act of Parliament...
Sets out what the truth is.
The truth has nothing to do with the law.
The law is the law and the truth
relates to evidence.
All right.
So when you are asked to take an
Act of Parliament under judicial review
Does that not mean that
we're not taking an Act of Parliament under
judicial review, because under 135 we're looking
at the whether or not there is a contravention
that's a factual and legal question.
If there was a contravention
under the Customs Act
We're not discussing the validity of the Customs Act.
My wording was was was poor.
What I meant to say is when you take
an Act of Parliament under judicial notice
according to the Canada Evidence Act
The Court has to take Acts of
Parliament as judicial notice
Does not mean that you
okay, where are they? Just we have two hours.
Okay, three hours for your two files.
It's nice if you want to raise all kinds of
preliminary questions, but you will have to get
to the meat that's what we have to decide.
very well. I will skip this one.
Very important question for me.
The original.. The first instance...
was in Federal Court and it was quite substantial
in terms of evidence provided. The appeal book
for the motion
for amendment, for summary judgment was substantial.
some 700 pages
my question to you is
given that my presentation today is... aims to
succeed at convincing you that there was an
overriding error and that you have to intervene
To what extent am I required to prove the facts
of the orginal motion
Um, in other words,
The only thing that is before us are the two Appeals.
Okay, the two appeal books.
For me it feels because one has several
so that's what before us.
I don't know yet how you want to proceed. So if you
were to proceed then I would be helping you by
saying "do you have evidence". We can't
talk to that in the air.
Of course. My question is in case I convince
you that that your intervention is required
Would this case be returned back to the Federal
Court for the determination.
Would you determine the facts? Where would I ...
We don't determine facts.
So would it go back to the Federal Court then?
It depends on what basis we intervene.
We can't make findings of fact.
So if all the facts don't need to be determined
and it's a pure question of law, we can decide it.
If it's not that, if there's a
reassessment of the evidence.
Then we send it back.
All right, very good. Perfect. That answers to my first trip
My last one is, I noticed a deficiency in my book of
authorities for the A-101 case,
which is the amendment,
I noticed that I entered the wrong
Section of the Federal Court Rules;
I would like to submit...
I don't have a book of authorities in 101
That's the Respondent's
ah, this thing... ok... and what
is it that is deficient?
Do you want to add something, is that it?
The Federal Court Rules I have I had quoted...
I meant to include Rule 76.
And 200 which are relevant to amendments.
Ok don't worry. We know the rules, we will find it.
All right. Very well.
So that ... I appreciate your time and patience
and we're ready to begin
I'd like to start with 101, which
is the amendment motion.
I will be in a few words, presenting the reason
why amendments are necessary
why amendments are done at all?
And how they fit with the rest of the preceding.
What's their purpose and meaning. Then I will
describe the overriding and palpable errors
that the Motion Judge made
and after this I will close by
By showing why you should intervene and change the
decision
Now... you have an hour and a half for the two appeals...
How are you... I don't know how much time you need
What was the... I just want you to have at
least ten minutes on each, or ten minutes to reply
Yes, my original time was much more than that,
I had to scale it down
by a lot.
So how much time do you think the two
Presentation
For both of two I think I will need
the entire time I may even go over time.
We won't go over time. We don't go over time.
I may not be able to finish.
in the
in
Ok, what I would suggest to you. Okay, and you
decide what you want to do, but I was suggest to you
that as a court of appeal, we know very well
what is the meaning of an amendment
and the rules has to do it?
If I were you, I would really dig immediately
into why there's an error.
because seriously
You can trust us. We know the rules
about amendments. Okay?
That's where you'll have more time. Yes.
However, I would like to very very briefly talk
about the meaning. Honorable Court, in a
ordinary action the purpose of the amendments
to the pleadings are to set the
agenda for for the proceding, that is to inform
both the defendant and of course as to what
the issues and questions are such that there
are no surprises to either party and such that
their the defendants rights are protected such
that they can prepare for the eventual trial
Um, according to the Federal Court Rules
amendments can be made at various stages of the
proceeding with or without leave of the Court.
As before the defendant even submits a reply.
An amendment can be made without even
Are we agreeing that in this case the statement of
Defense had been
Yes,
so that's a that's a reply. So that means you need
the leave of the Court,
correct?
Okay, so let's get on with
My point is that even after that the
statement of defense is is entered.
The parties can still consent.
No, you need leave of the Court.
The Court will consider
If there is a consent, but it's still
the court that decides
All right, wery well. I will then skip to the palpable errors.
So, on the motion for amendment, the Motion Judge
the most visible palpable error is that he considered
evidence in deciding the motion which is something that
he is not permitted to consider according with the Federal
Court Rules, and also according to the Ontario civil procedure.
Okay, why don't you turn to the rules which rules
says that he doesn't have the right to look at that and
Your Honour, based on precedent of Bauer
... that would be in my
Authorities
That's in 101, and which case
Page number 23 of the authorities book
I don't have pages and that's what I'm
it would be at the bottom of the page, bottom line.
Yes, but page 23 for me is a Tax Excise
the Excise Tax Act
the latest Authority book
Yeah.
So book of authorities 101, page 23 for me is Excise Tax
My friend has a book.
has the same book with different pages.
Okay Bauer, ok..
I don't have the same index in my as my colleague
So you have the same one. You don't have the Bauer?
Okay. Okay. I don't know why
I'm saying one may see it.
Yes.
This is one of two
your friend to 102
know. This is the book for 102.
But you said you were dealing with 101.
I'm dealing with 101, but somehow the printing.
They must have fallen the the front pages.
The covers.
Okay.
No problem.
You're referring to the decision.
Which paragraph
paragraph 16?
Stinky. Yes.
When determining whether amendment should be allowed
to the judge [unintelligible] matter to ask
whether the amendment would be
capable of being struck
the test for being struck in the Fiddle Court Rules.
in 2121
But there are several paragraphs.
And only the paragraph no reasonable cause of action. You don't look at evidence all the other paragraph you look at it.
Yes
generous, correct.
So if the church things that there's no chance of success or taxation or and that's the another paragraph that you want one where is entitled to look at it?
Yes. However in those in this case those were not considered for those other points the church didn't look what was immaterial or redundant material. He didn't look at whether there was candles. He was no language like that in his decision.
Oh, okay. Let's look at the decision.
is order
Yes, power
power antenna.
Yes, so that's the same case you refer to
yes.
And the proposed extending that came to not demonstrate their reasonable chance of success.
I guess you're under the test for
for emotions to amend is
I was
I think most authoritatively rested by the federal court by the Supreme Court and Imperial tobacco.
Yes,
which is records by these other cases.
Yes.
very little case is that
page
So yeah, but that was also that 22 a 2.18 it was the there was no reasonable cause of action so there he don't look at evidence.
well, perhaps it would then be
helpful for me to look at why MMS are necessary what their life cycle is why why and when evidence should not considered in a case that emotion to amend would be
Dismissed that is the client will be blocked from being heard. The plaintiff can always submit.
That many men as a new option.
As a new statement of Clans to pursue the same dispute because just by blocking the amendment does not result. It is just so the plaintiff would then
get it as a new action.
based on the same material thoughts
It's always because
you say if he doesn't allow the amendments.
Their claim as it was is still before the court. Is that what you
said is, correct?
Okay. So the same before the court is still and that brings us to the second appeal.
Because you see these things are very much linked.
Yeah.
But the Amendments the proposed amendments are are left in the air. They're not
having discarded.
Allow them you're saying that they still exist in that there's still a cause of action.
That's available to you.
There's something adding to something that goes over there.
Well, you are one of the Amendments doesn't produce any costs about
which one
that is the one that
All right proposed on them.
You're adding two defendants.
I might put a defenders in their capacity as a crowned as agents of the crown.
Okay, 25 just by I'm looking now at the age of 48 Bill booking.
That is Amanda the underlying
yes,
which one has the new cause of action?
The claim is that the CBSA circulates under 16(c).
The CBSA circulates an internal operations bulletin.
and
so that's 60
16(c) is on page 60
page. Yes, 16(c) is on page 161
I have a home page
60.
Is that the CBSA circulates an
internal operational bulletin?
For me, it's page 60.
So I don't know why but okay.
So that's the important thing.
We have the right paragraph.
So you're saying this is a new cause an action
It's a new cause of action, it alleges that the
CBSA is involved in money laundering
but that's not it's just
Isn't it just a remedy? Because you've already
said that you thought that you was
enabling
I had not mentioned money laundering.
Money laundering is a new cause of action
in the Amendments. Before then, in the
original Statement of Claim
I had suspected that it was something that's
good. So what else is a new cause
and there's a lot
of underlining.
Yes, but most of this is really.
All related you see you cannot come to 16 and plain unless you've had allegation in the first part.
So there are allegations that are linked to these.
Because you see like that these this is not a new cause of action. It's just
you're making education of fat that would bring you into whatever remedy you're asking.
Well, if I find religion that CBS is a criminal organization.
Okay, let's not lose too much time on this. Okay. So here saying let's say 17 a is a new plane because it's finished.
There before that was there before.
So that this new apart from that because you didn't ask for 2004 we did ask for 15,000.
I'm just not seeing.
New cause of action that would stand on their own.
the honor this
without finding specifically the paragraph because they're so many that I had touched the allegation of
money laundering and criminal organization are new.
Okay, and what what's the point of this do you were saying that these would stand on their own in another proceedings?
They can be pursued on their own. So
now there's not Time bar.
You have the time limitation issue. You cannot take an action, you know 20 years from the date of the events and say I have this
is correct. But at the time that they maybe was proposed.
I had only just learned about the money laundering.
Okay, you can always what you're saying is that you can
take a separate action. Is that what you're
saying? Well, yes.
Okay. So why don't you that's what you say
because that would not be the most vicious and and this cost way to reach Justice.
Okay, that's your argument for why you made an error?
Because we have to make sense of this.
Well, you are my argument is that he used evidence where shouldn't have?
the court
I'm sorry. My presentation is
no I'm just trying to make sure that I don't want to miss what you're saying.
You started with that. Okay that you should not have look at that. I thought
well, you said that he may not look at evidence on
2.181 a but it can't accept there's a they are exception under eight for to addiction. For example.
Well, they're not stated in their rules. You're on.
Yeah, but they're stated in the case of
that's very cute in their role. It doesn't say anything that the rule is being construed by case law.
and
if I'm not mistaken, it's fun for
That but anyway, I
am
operating we continue
operating under the guidance of the Supreme Court.
Says very clearly and without doubt.
All
okay. Let's let's
continue
and 23
What is impossible to enumerate all the factors that a judge must take into participation determining whether an adjustment?
Where is it whether it is just a given case to authorizing Amendment. The general rules is that an amendment should be allowed at any state or the action for the purpose of determining their real questions and controversy between the department provided notably that the allowance will not result in an injustice.
For the other party and not capable of being compensated by an award of costs.
That's good. That's good. As I told you don't lose too much time on the law. We can read it
in case you're under that is oh I have for
this presentation
that's that's
wrong in using evidence
and that would be an airplane.
specifically
Or it might be an error in his that is a reasons are not clear enough as to which paragraph he was looking at.
Well the owner in a few words I can demonstrate why looking at sectional 106 which is what the defendant proposed is flawed to look at that point. And that's for
the amendment.
No, one of the Customs out.
Yes, but we're now looking at are you
on the amendment? I'm only doing with the members so far. I'm understanding that. We're addressing these two cases separately.
No, but what your hour and a half is for the two of them?
It's three hours for both.
Yes. We are only dealing with
so what
do you want to say about so
many six the pendant proposed officers wear?
Would not be liable.
For their actions under the custom job.
Yes.
Nobody do not be liable. Not under the customer's of
Activities.
Yes
under the Customs act and yes, they are nothing for someone
okay, if they are not in pursuant.
The Crown cannot be the vicariously liable.
You cannot sue the Crown for something done outside of their duties. You can sue them, but you cannot sue the Crown.
Well the crown
either they are inside their Duty and the crown because of the employer are liable for them.
Okay, they cherish me or they're not doing it on their Duty then they are responsible for it.
Well, they're not doing it in their personal capacity.
What if they're doing a frog that's what you're saying? They're doing a fraud. It's and it's outside of the customer. You're trying to get out of Windows 6 to get out of Windows 6. You have to get out of the crust on that and you have to get out of the vicarious liability of the front.
You know, the word is
not really
cares means you are responsible for your agents and employees for what he did in the performance of their Duty.
See what
and
so you could sue them personally.
And that may not come under one was six if it is outside of their Duty.
But that's not be within the jurisdiction of our core because we only can entertain that kind of action against the crown itself,
correct?
The other person assuming that the thought is true.
Assuming that the fact is traded
are true.
Fraud would have to be one of the tools that these officers are allowed to employ to implement the custom job.
They have a number of activities that they can employers actually searches questioning.
Okay, and
that's why the section 106
does not protect them from
and how do you
Why do you think that the Crown can be liable
for something that is not within their duty?
It's not within their duty of anything to do fraud
They were doing the fraud, they were justifying
it as implementing the Customs Act
so their cover was their duty
If we had met on the street and they asked me for
my coins, I would not have given it to them as
as a person, as an individual.
I only gave him my coins because they were
Do you have any case though
that you can sue them
And there is case of fraud and it
would not apply to the Crown
the one authority I can point to
is my book of authorities for 102
authority for 102 and I am referring to...
Zolotow v. Canada, page 46
page 46 ... [unintelligible]
Paragraph
the case that I have
Now for 46 I have
[unintelligible]
yes, I've gone to the
That's the one that used to be 101 but became 102
[unintelligible]
It's Zolotow
Zolotow
just a second.
I don't have a 46 in the other one so it has to be this one
Yes, it is one of the longer table.
Yes and my page 46.
Oh, is it because you didn't?
Did you just put pages without the
front and just a page out of the text?
Yes.
ok
so the point you're making about that case
though just to bring us back to the
The point is that under paragraph 30 if illegal
acts are really done from the motive other than an
honest drive to execute a statutory or legal duty
Then, the Public Authorities Act is no
defense for the acts complained of
of are not done in the intended execution of a
statute, but only in the pretended execution
thereof.
So that's why you're saying
the Customs Act does not apply
because you're alleging that the officers
were committing a fraud
Fraud would not be one of the tools that
they can employ they were however using
pretending to act as Customs officers pretending
that these coins where goods so that they
could seize them and request their
I understand your point very well.
Where I'm concerned is how you can sue the Crown
for something that's outside of their duties.
Uh, and that's the Crown Liabilities Act
Do you have...
just a second have you put Council
the Crown Liability section?
No
I have the Crown Liability
under the authorities 101, page 11
at page 12
Liability and Civil Salvage
The Crown is liable for the damage for which,
if it were a person, it would be liable.
any other province in respect of a tort
committed by a servant of the Crown
the fault... I don't know if it's fraud
Fraud is a tort, is it not?
That's what I'm saying to you,
we'll need to look at that
If they're acting outside of their duties totally
Normally an employer would not be responsible
so we have to look at case law
just saying don't have it before you
before us we'll have to look at
Good. So what we'll do is to make sure that you have
we don't want to construe 3(1)
Okay, 3(a)(i) without you being able
to make submissions on it
So I would give you
Or Thursday with the end of the day next Monday
Be a good you can write to the Court and say
here are some authorities that I would like
to submit to show that a fraud
would come within 3(a)(i)
by Monday?
Yes, the end of the day on Monday, that okay?
I'm not able to I am out of the my home country for a week.
I live in Mexico for much
of the time I came here specially
Um, can I have two weeks?
Yes it just that we won't be so long as
the case is not closed. We cannot render
a decision. If I give you two weeks.
I'm just saying I don't know when you'll
get your decision because we sit everywhere.
and the time to write your case
might be next week, so
well, in any case I have I have no way of
sitting down and looking at this until
at the very least Wednesday
the earliest that I'll be back home is Wednesday
Okay, so, okay. You'll have to wait.
that means, see the calendar
That's June 7, is that ok for you?
And you understand what we're looking for.
Um, my understanding is that you are
looking for representations as to why
the Crown would be
and just to be sure
My coleague pointed out. We're looking at 3(b)(i)
because it's not the province of Quebec.
The other province, okay, so 3(b)(i)
so why 3(b)(i) applies
in the case of would apply to make
the Crown viable for fraud
for fraud commited outside of their duty
Are we making the assumption that if they
were working on the clock and working on?
and working on the seizure
that they are outside of their duty?
that's what you are supposed to
I'm giving you a chance to argue this point.
provide some authority
I will
Thank you.
At this stage, we're not making any assumptions
that is all I have for A-101
for representations, I would like to move on to 102
So, 102
and obviously
the other side will have the right to respond
I'll see what they need in terms of time,
but it's something that we normally know
well, so we should be
quite good with the case
Your Honour without further ado
I'd like to get into 102
there are numerous palpable errors
to discuss the first one
the judge was required to find whether
section 102
let me these backtrack and explain
and explain the larger picture
in the 102 and the
motion for summary judgment
the defendant made representations
to guide the way the case was considered. He
conflated
an appeal under section
132... 135
135 with the purpose of the entire action
He represented that
Wherever a section 135 claim appears,
The preceding is a special type of proceeding that
is  outside of those defined under the
Federal Court Rules.
He said that it is not neither an
application for review, neither
An ordinary action, neither a simplified action, neither a class action.
He alleges that an appeal is just a different type
of proceeding where the Cout is being asked
to reconsider
anew the decision that was before
the Minister. He represents that
the task before the judge was to decide
in the Minister's place, based on new evidence
whether there was a contravention or not
Guiding the preceeding this way can only lead to
an outcome in his favor
and it is incorrect the... an appeal
Under 135 is simply one claim.
that can be entered as part of the
ordiary action. The preceding type
that you're allowed to make a 135
claim under is an ordinary action
and the appeal is only one of the claims available
However, there is nothing in the Customs Act
that precludes a plaintiff from
from joining other claims that arise from
the same facts, from the same details.
Do you agree because the judge
rely on two cases, okay
Starway and...
I'm trying to find the decision
Starway and Nguyen?
yes
now, these two cases deal with
an action or a negations
contensting the amount of penalty.
Do you contest the amount of
penalty in your action?
No,
okay. So do you agree that if we follow
these cases because in the Customs Act
it is clear that to
challenge a decision on the penalty
you have to go to a judicial.
I do not.
the penalty
Yes, I do not.
So you contest that
Yes.
Okay, even though you're not joining
Correct.
So
Your Honour, let me address this
point exactly, specifically
you have that at page 18 of your
authorities
I believe Starway was
In Starway, there were two issues.
There was both whether the issue that there
was an infraction, and also the issue of whether
the minister could keep the money
He, the judge specifically looked.
And explained that it makes no
sense to allow the defendant to keep
the terms of release if the decision cannot stand.
I'm sorry.
The one that you've included
If one intends to dispute the amount of penalty,
one must apply for judicial review
Before it has been determined that the case
committed. This is an anomaly. Okay.
and everybody has said it's an anomaly but
Well, it may be an anomaly. I am referring to
Starway at my authority page 44 and 45.
Specifically paragraphs 27 and 28
Okay
Starway
27 and 28 of Starway
Ok, again I don't have the right...
page 48?
44 and 45
47 and thank you
At paragraph 27... in accordance with section 135
of the Act, this is an ordinary action. The only
special rule imposed was that whether Mr. Starway
made an untrue statement
I will deal with this a little later.
The amount of penalty is not an issue.
This is a trial, not paper review.
Yes, and where does he say that
you can dispute the penalty in an action?
the next paragraph, paragraph 28 begins with
"The next issue the imposition of the penalty,
not the amount thereof".
"The defendants submit that at
best I can only declare..." and so on and so on.
At the end of the paragraph 28 Starways says
"Since there was no infraction of the Customs Act,
it follows that defendants cannot
keep the amount forfeited"
Yeah, but that's a different question. I was
talking to you about the amount of the penalty
I know that in your action, you do discuss
that the amount was reduced by the minister.
three hundred instead of the other amount
let's discus the remedies
once there is no contravention, what can you do?
Obviously, there's no contravention.
There's no contravention!
The defendant states that the only available
remedy for the Court is to declare whether
or not there was a contravention
He specifically says
So you're trying to say under 135, what are the remedies?
But what we're looking at now is whether you can
you can can use the vehicle of application
Or an ordinary action to contest
the amount of the penalty.
Well, they are
but there's an issue
it is a claim
I would like to point out ACL.
I'm not I have to say I'm not 100% I
just want to make sure we get your point on this.
I would like to point out to ACL
as another example where
ACL Canada
bringing it back to your particular case
what exactly are you saying
I'm saying that just because
a claim under Section 135 is contained
within an ordinary action,
There is no provision in the Customs Act to make
it the exclusive claim that can be
made in that ordinary action,
The Customs Act itself does not limit, does not say
that you may not have another claim that is
related to the same facts
That's clear. And what's not clear is
if it is clear in Customs Act
certain issues need to be dealt
with by judicial review
certain decision under the Customs Act needs to be
contested by way of judicial
That's that's the problem I'm trying to eliminate
Is there anything in your claim
That would be comparable to the claims that
were made in the two cases on which
the judge relies.
Which is just Starway and Nguyen
Yes, there are multiple claims in the same action
Is there any of those claims in your action?
That are the same as the claims that were
dealt with in Starway and Nguyen
Well, they're not the same claims.
I think that's the point that you you want to make.
It's not what is dealt with in those cases
was something that needed to be
done by application, not by action
if I were to address this issue of application vs
action, the Customs Act does not even require
the amount of to be disputed by way of application
Yes, but that's
that's what it's supposed to be.
This decision have to be about federal office.
contested by way of judicial review
if you're seeking damages, there
can be a conversion
But all this must be done, you know, there can be a
conversion if you want to get damages
from that decision.
And this is why I was pointing to ACL kind of so,
At ACL, which paragraph
At page 42 of your book of authority
page 42
in ACL the judge looked at section 135 claim
and concluded at paragraph 61
third line from the bottom, that
under the section 135 the plaintiff's action
in this regard must be dismissed.
within that regard
which Regard
in regard to section 135
[reads ACL Canada para 61]
Okay, so
why is that of interest to us? It seems to confirm with the judge was saying
so under 135.
That specific claim can be dismissed.
However, he went on to consider the claim under
133 in the following paragraph, paragraph 6...
Actually the second following paragraph, 63
[reads ACL Canada para 62]
and 63
[continues reading ACL Canada para 62]
So he seems to be saying the
contrary to what you're saying
He's saying that section 135 does
not give the minister
That's right. And he says either 135 or otherwise under the act or the general jurisdiction of the Court.
which which means that if if
if relief sought was within the general
jurisdiction of the Court, he would he would
have to consider it.
He did not consider that relief only
because he was concerning section 133
but you were relying on a passage.
where you said the judge confirmed that
the Court could give could make an order
for that. There's no money for [unintelligible]
That was the previous case that you called.
And now they're saying we don't have that
jurisdiction. So these two cases...
will have to go and look at okay, because
they seem to be contradictory
he also replies that if another remedy within the
Action was within the general jurisdiction of
the Court, he would have to consider it
Yes. He says it's not within the jurisdiction
to say no forfeiture, that's contrary
to what you just said before
that's specific claim you are right,
you know, what we'll read them because
I found
To summarize, you're saying that
we should be distinguishing
Starway and Nguyen
You know, no I'm not let me just finish my thought
your I think saying that the judge was wrong and in
using those two cases to rely on,
because you're saying
because of your case is definately can be
distinguished and you're relying on ACL
to say that the court has
more jurisdiction to deal with these matters. Is that is that what it is
it is, however in
yes, so we based on ACL the Court does
have more jurisdiction to consider
your claims
section 133 which is an additional claims
so I want to make sure I understand your points. Okay?
Starway for a second... in Starway, page 45
continue our reading Starway
after we talked about
he pointed out the fact that he says he
can't keep the money that there's no infraction
kind of playing on [unintelligible] ...
dollars should be returned
Now, so this is over the comments of the judge
did he actually order the money thing returned?
Do you you actually have the judgments
That will go on and even though they may not
have jurisdiction to deal with something just
just point out that ... crap, as long as I make a
decision, I should do something
even though I may not be able to
order you do something
I don't know if there was an order or
it was just his comment that this seems to be logical thing
thing you really should do.
So we'll look at that. We'll find the judgement
Because otherwise these two cases
would be contradictory
I would like to also a point out
in paragraph 63 of ACL
the judge did
towards the end, he ends with "I conclude that an
order should go setting aside the Minister's
determination made under section 133 and
referring both matters back
for reconsideration by another adjudicator"
So that means that even in an ordinary action,
Section 133 was good,
you know what would read the case because
that's why normally you shouldn't have
a page like this. We don't have to have
the whole case here have it all.
but we'll look at. So that's your first
What else do you want to say about 102?
about joinder
It's again.
joinder under 106 of the Rules
Well, there's no claim under 106
I'm not talking of the Customs Act,
I'm talking about the Rules.
Yes, that will be Rule 101
of the Federal Court Rules
Rule 101 paragraph 1
"Subject to rule 302, a party to a proceeding may
request relief against another party to the
same proceeding in respect of more than one claim"
So it would be incorrect. So it was a palpable
and overriding erorr for the Motion Judge
To disallow this Rule and claim that only a section
135 claim can be made in an ordinary action.
when the Rules of the Federal Court
obviously say otherwise
anything else
Yes.
You're going very well.
Your Honour,
I'd like to point out Rule 106 of the
Federal Court Rules
complication or delay or would prejudice a
party, the Court may order separate claims
Or many orders that came to be split or to
be dealt with in a more convenient fashion.
So with your saying is he should have split it.
If you thought that this was
completed as a dismissal,
that's right.
Okay.
Because just ignoring and dismissing claims
without looking at them.There's no justice in it
it's not in the interest of justice
okay.
I'd like to point out.
the Excise Tax Act
but this goes again to multiple
preceding
proceedings to multiple claims in the same proceeding
Yeah
section...
the Excise Tax Act
I don't have my I wouldn't need a few seconds
to find the section that I'm talking about
Take your few seconds
It's in your book of authorities?
You have have just 15... page 15, to
25, but I think 25 is the definition of
money, because you're on 15
I may have messed up...
are you looking for 81.28?
on page 18
yes... 81.29 was in my notes
Is your point that the
rule concerning joinder apply?
to these actions, that's 81.28(3)
my case... doesn't seem to be..
I am a little...
You know what? What we'll do, because
you're almost at the end of your time...
We'll break for 5 minutes
You collect your thoughts, and you
pick the things you've not yet said
That would be fantastic, thank you
order
order!
Court is resumed
Thank you for the extra time
I'd like to continue. With respect to joinder,
The Excise Tax Act s.81.28(3)(a)
Gives us an example how if
Parliament intended to limits
the claims available in an ordinary action,
they can, with specific language.
In the Excise Tax Act, they basically
exclude the rules by saying
"the rules concerning joinder of
parties and causes of action..."
do not apply except for the joinder
of appeals under that Part"
Which means
Which means that under the Customs Act,
since no such limitation is given,
it cannot be implied.
The Parliament does have the ability to
I like to move on to the next point the
next clear error; the Motion Judge ignored
ignored the plaintiff's evidence
on several occasions.
The first one would have been
the Currency Act section 11.
Which is at authorities book page
That's where you wanted to say
that the statute is evidence.
The Currency Act is not evidence, it's the law.
You say that he ignored the
relevant section of the law
It is evidence my... understanding of the Act is that
The Acts that I bring, that I present
to the court, with my case,
are part of my evidence but
statutes are another their statutes.
So don't worry. It means that it
might be an error... still an error.
not to consider
relevant section
so you're saying why is it relevant and
it is relevant because specifically
That's on page 27?
11..
That's 29... No person shall, except in
accordance with a license granted by the
minister, melt down, break down or
use otherwise than as currency
any coin that is current and legal tender in Canada
I would underline "to use otherwise, then as currency"
What do you want to do with that?
It is relevant because the Currency Act itself
tells that currency cannot be treated as "goods".
It cannot be used as goods or something else.
It's only a token of currency.
so you're saying you should
have discussed your argument
The coins you had in this case
are the US coins, right?
Are they legal tender in Canada?
They're not legal tender in Canada.
How does 11(1) apply?
there's a parallel was drawn and
it was not contested by other party that
coins of the United States, the treatment
of the United States and in Canada
are parallel and equivalent legislations
and the rules that would apply to coins in
corresponding coins in Canada
also applying to currency of the United States
tell us which Act? People cannot
agree on the law without...
Canada has similar coins as the ones I had
which are $50 gold coins and five one dollar coins?
So the point is that if the Canadian coins cannot
can be not not treated cannot be treated
as goods or as something other than currency,
then the US coins cannot either.
On what basis you say that?
Your Honor the the United States public law
that is the that is the corresponding law of the
Canadian one, the Currency Act,
states this. It has the same
Yes, but the US act only applies in the US.
And the Canadian act applies in Canada.
so I'm not understanding why the fact that
If you US coins are not currency
in Canada, a legal tender
they are currency in the United States.
Yes, but we're in Canada now
If they were Canadian coins,
they could also not be considered "goods"
for the reasons of section 11
They are not Canadian Coins.
The question of my colleague is "Why would this act
apply to US
because it shows that Canadian coins are treated
in a specific way
Yes,
and it was never any contention any
it's an anology you're making, because
this section cannot apply directly
The defendant agreed that coins of the
we don't care that he agrees or not.
If it's a matter of law we need to
know what's your position
well in that case. I would have to present the
equivalent section from the United States Act
The US coins are not tender in Can
Okay. So what you're saying is paragraph?
section 11
would apply if they were coins in Canadian currency
you say by analogy,
we should treat the US the same way because
the US act as absolutely no application here,
correct.
Okay, so it's by analogy.
Next one. I like to point out that.
the motion judge errored in accepting the
defendant's explanation that
the Customs Act applies to all Goods
which is not true, they
the Customs Act is activated specifically
by the Excise Tax Act.
It doesn't just come into force out of the blue for
everything that you bring into Canada.
For instance. If you import food or water
or even my own vehicle that I was driving that day
I was not required to report it to declare it
as imported in Canada, even
though I did import it in Canada.
I was not required to declare it. I did
not declare it. It's not a problem.
The question is why is this?
because it is a good it is quite valuable.
And so on so we would the
tests that he applied to the coins.
The reason goods in general are not
immediately subject to the Customs Act
is because the Customs Act power is
given by the Excise Tax Act section 51
which which tells us that that authorities page 15
about 15 or 16
we're described where
maybe we can be more precise where
of course section 50(a)
sorry... 50(1)(b)
and then 51(1)
just a second one. I would just read it.
What do you say that section does?
This section tells us what the
purpose of the Customs Act
is and is what activates the Customs Act
to act on things that are imported
So it's only on goods that are
I'm not sure that I understand what you're saying
because 50 says that there shall be imposed
a consumption tax.
on goods imported in Canada payable in
accordance with the provision of the Custom Act
Yes.
it doesn't say that you don't have to declare
something under the Customs Act
because of the excise tax
It says that the Customs Act is unnecessary in the case.
No, no, it does not. You're correct.
This section does not.
Okay. So which section because you're
section 51.
Shows the exemptions. 51(1) - the tax imposed by
section 50 does not apply on the sale or
importation of goods mentioned in Schedule III
Yes. So the fact that there's no tax
Why does it mean that you don't have
because there is no tax to be collected
in accordance with the Customs Act.
We'll have to look at the provisions
of the first [unintelligible]
I don't think it leaves you.
determine whether
Do you recall the provision of the Customs Act that
says you declare only the goods on
which tax is payable?
The Customs Act does not do that. It does not activate itself.
No, but it doesn't say that you have to declare
only if there's tax
It does not.
That is not the Customs Act's
job to do. The Customs Act only comes into
effect in case there is tax to be collected
And in case there is tax to be collected,
it is to be collected in accordance with the
Customs Act. That means you have to declare it and
you have to pay the tax.
Okay, that's your position.
That's fine. Your next point?
And paragraph 51 at Schedule III part IX
Page 20, which is one of the exemptions.
and on page 20 part 5
It should be Part XI of Schedule III. It's on page 22
exemptions from importation tax
that is to be collected according
to the Customs Act
So paragraph 3 and 4 of part XI state
that British and Canadian coins
and foreign gold coin
are exempted from importation tax
and the application of the Customs tax.
subparagraph 4 of part XI says
coin of any metal of authorized weight and
design issued for use as currency
under the authority of the government of any
country. So this would include the United States
are exempt from
a importation tax and therefore collection of
the importation tax under the Customs Act
And it follows that if if there is no tax to be paid,
and the Customs Act does not need to be enforced.
There's no point to declare things that not need to be
taxed and this is why
your point if I take it is that
no tax imposed on good, you do not have to
declare it when we come to the Border.
That is correct.
Following that logic, if someone arrived
at the border with fresh fruit
From another country you're saying
it wouldn't have to.
declare that because no tax on it
In so far as the fruits... let's not
use fruit as an example
because there's a agricultural
but where does that fit into the Customs Act?
Fruits will not be declared under Customs.
It would be declared under the Agriculture Act.
you're saying a separate Act
requires you to declare fruit
Yes, but not one for taxation purposes, but
for germs and for other certification purposes,
well, let's use a car, your personal car or an
object that is not subject to the Agricultural Act
Like the coins like inner objects, the car
that I was driving was not subject to
the importation tax
But but did you buy that car in the United States?
I did not.
so guess that depends on what
the word "imported" means.
Does the word "imported" only mean bringing goods
that you acquired outside the country
as opposed to returning Goods that came from
Canada and are bringing back to Canada
You Honour, I believe that's incorrect.
I believe the distinction is not
on what "importation" means
but on whether a tax payable.
The car was no doubt imported because it
was outside the country in the morning,
It was inside the country in the afternoon.
... semantics ...
so, can you remind me of the section, my
material doesn't have it and I'm going to
go look for it later my book of
authorities, unfortunately, or
There's a problem with it. Yeah, so, can you
just repeat to me exactly
So Schedule III Part IX...
Part XI
That's where I wasn't clear and I didn't have it.
I'm sorry. It just Schedule II Part XI Points 3 and 4.
Okay. Thank you.
If you bring for example other foodstuffs that are
for example chips or things that are not subject
to agricultural controls.
You do not have to report it to report it.
In fact many people drive to cross the border
to buy their groceries and they come back.
Does not have to be reported. The same day that I
came in with these coins, I have also bought some
bottle of water and some headache medication. I
had a headache that day. Medication is also exempt
from taxation.
which is the reason why I did not have to report it.
My car did not have to be reported because tax on it
had already been paid when the car was initially
imported into Canada. So
it was not subject because it was not something on which
you had already paid the tax
because there was no tax owing, there
was no tax due to be collected
It's not because it wasn't imported
Okay, so we got your point now we have to hurry
because you have to complete this in 5 minutes
Based on
the evidence submitted by the defendant which was
only the Customs Act, is the only evidence he had
to offer in support of his position that the goods
are money, the judge found that
that position and that evidence is not helpful to
to his to his point and he found that in fact
according to the Currency Act, the coins are in
fact currency and legal tender in the United States or
and they are not "goods"
according to the Customs Act
well, he found that they were
not according to the evidence
submitted by the defendant
Okay, what's your point
in order for him to find that they were "goods",
he had to introduce some evidence of his own.
that was nothing that was based on what the
defendant said. The defendant never...
can you point the paragraph
you used the word "evidence" [unintelligible]
that's why I don't understand you
Are you refering to how he defined "money"?
Yes, the definition of "money" from
the Excise Tax Act
Okay, so
You mean that he's bringing up an
argument that was not put to him
Is that what you're saying.. it wasn't argued?
That is correct
Okay, so it was a new argument that
was not put by the parties before?
Okay, that's a different a. Yeah.
And which paragraph?
Okay decision.
paragraph 60 of the decision
That's the definition of "money" in the Excise Tax
and that was definately before him...
the "Excise Tax Act"
this definition was not, Your Honour
No, but that Act was before him. Once you put an Act
The judge has to look at that the Act as a whole.
He cannot just read at the At and
not look at the definition
However, the defendant did not submit that this
is the reason why he thinks the coins are
yes, but it's a matter of law.
See, matters of law you can agree you can say...
it's the judge who gets to decide
So the Act was before him, it's not like he
looked Act that he didn't know about
This definition of money is not normative
Its context is specific to section 123
Unfortunately this is a very long section; the
definitions is very long. I did not include it in my
authority, but at the heading of it says that this
definition only applies for that subsection
It's not a general definition of "money", which
does not exist. In Canadian law we do not have a
legal definition for what "money" is this.
This is only a placeholder
to save rewriting the same long paragraph
Okay, so it cannot be just for the purpose
of 123. It has to be for the purpose of Part IX.
The definition
is adapted in part IX subsection 123. So what
you're saying, it applies only to the part or
wherever it says that it applies.
That is correct.
Not in another act.
That's correct.
Okay, that's good.
So what did he do that with that? I don't think that he
so this was the only basis on which he
found the coins can be considered "goods"
Nothing in the defendants or the plaintiff's
representations gave
Any evidence that they can be considered "goods"?
Too long. How many arguments you have left?
I have
just raise them, because we we cannot
okay Your Honor the para of 53 of the reasons where
the judge followed an analysis of what coins are
currency, but he concludes that reporting under
section 12 of the Customs Act.
It is the
53 talks only about the Proceeds Act and the Mint
Act, he doesn't talk about the Customs Act.
About half way down, 4th line down, he says "the
reporting obligations provided for in section
12(1) of the Customs Act are therefore triggered"
Yes, but you were under 10,000.
My point is that I believe this is a
it doesn't apply to you
It doesn't apply to me, but if it should.
The limit of 10,000 should apply to me.
Yes, so
in case I did have more than 10,000
I should have had to to report them.
Yes, but he does say that it is triggered
Yes, he uses the words "the reporting obligations
provided under section 12 of the Customs Act"
his analysis pertained to
I don't see the word Custom Act here
He uses Proceeds Act
in the first sentence, but the second sentence
he talks about the reporting obligations.
the reporting obligation provided for
at section 12(1) of the Proceeds Act
"Proceeds Act"
Not Customs
My decision says... Customs Act
Rivoalen: Really?
Gauthier: Really?
(Gauthier) That's incredible
(Gauthier) Counsel, do you have...
(Rivoalen) On the...
(Peterson) Yeah, mine says Proceeds
Frankly.. ok, so we agree that
if the official version is Proceeds Act
that would be the correct, yes
Perfect. So we'll leave that.
Okay, so
so this point falls
It may have been corrected.
I know that this was corrected...
could the judge have ammended that
at some point for errors?
Not that I recall.
Okay, that's fine.
Ok, go ahead, sorry
Did you get this from the website,
instead of the official version
Your Honour, there were so many, I'm not sure where
Because, you see, what they transcribe on the website
they could make a mistake in transcribing
This would be a huge mistake to make
that from the official version
it's definitely Proceeds
Well, I will take your word. I believe this is a huge
mistake to make and it would be impossible
So let's go to the next one
the next one.
In paragraph 57...
of the decision
he does talk about what activates the Customs Act,
but overlooks specifically section 50(1)(b)
Which deals with the importation;
he only generally looks at
The Excise Tax Act, probably, maybe, might not even if
you can write. Okay next.
Because we don't have a choice. We have other
appeals this afternoon and
your friend is entitled to his time.
Your Honour, on a
motion for summary judgment
It should be
should not be granted in case
a confident opinion cannot be made.
in order to grant a summary judgement the
judge needs to have confidence in his
so sufficient evidence must be available that he
can confidently determine the matter.
If the matter cannot be determined confidently
Yes, but he felt that he had it
He said that he felt it,
however, he had
that one is a very difficult point to convince us
Is there a paragraph
Yes, Your Honour, paragraph 58 of the decision
I'm sorry, it's 68.
"having concluded both the Customs and Proceeds
Act apply concurrently. I will address the issue
of overlapping provisions."
And then he discusses the at paragraph 70,
"The courts have recognized that
the scope and application..."
Okay.
And he talks about conflict and overlap.
Okay,
so that's the wording of conflict.
Yes.
You're saying that his use of the words conflict
and overlap shows uncertainty
Absolutely.
Another paragraph, 65
"the plaintiff has not argued that the
coins, if found to be goods,
are exempt from reporting requirements,
set out at subsection 12(1)"
however, the plaintiff did exactly this, in the
page 118, which is part of the motion record.
So
So, page 118 [uninteligible], paragraph 9
Exactly that point,
okay.
So 65 page paragraph 9. Okay next.
You are pet the other significant errors that had.
felt was
an appeal under section 135 is
an appeal for judicial review by the Customs Act
So it means that there should have been a standard
of review stated, and he should have reviewed
the decision of the minister.
Not to try to reach his own decision
based on fresh evidence.
No, but because it's on fresh evidence,
it cannot be a judicial review.
But there is
un-french that a new evidence.
That's the purpose of doing it by way of action.
No, Your Honor.
but as part of
I'm very sorry. I have to disagree.
No, okay, but let's do this quickly
I'm faced with an impossible task of
proving a huge case in a very short time.
It's three hours.
I understand.
We are bound by the Chief Justice duration.
We cannot extend.
May I request an adjurment?
NO!
Would you make your point the
last point talking about the judicial review
Your Honour, in order to do a judicial review, the
judge would have had to consider the Minister's
consideration of the evidence before him,
and whether he reached a conclusion in
an intelligible manner
according to Dunsmuir Supreme Court Case 2008
We're aware of Dunsmuir
so the minister's decision
would have had to be intelligible
so that the plaintiff has a chance to
defend against it
and such that a reviewing court
would understand how it was made.
He was not deciding the action
he was deciding a summary judgment
based on a question of law.
So if you say it was not enough to
determine that question to
to strike the action, say that,
and then we'll pass the next one.
Because there are two different things.
He was not deciding the action.
He was deciding whether there was a genuine issue.
Yes a genuine issue about whether or not
the coins were "goods" that had to be declared.
the claims in the the action were
that a review was requested,
so he had to find whether the review would be
I think we understand your point.
What I didn't mention is that in order
My point is that the Minister's
Decision is unintelligible
and this alone should have been ground to find that
the decision should be set aside,
even before looking at whether the goods.
That is all I have.
You didn't need an extra adjournment.
Well, that is all I can say
in the time that I've been given.
Yes, and that's been...
you've covered all your points.
So thank you very much.
You've done very well and you will have
a short time for replaying after you hear the other
Okay?
Thank you.
So, Your Honor in terms of the amendment appeal
If you've read the Crown's
memorandum of fact and law.
The issue is really covered all very squarely by
the decision of this Court in [Taleb?]
and I don't propose to take you through it,
that sets out the standard of review very clearly.
And in fact, this case rests squarely
on the [Taleb?] case.
is the only case that cited for the proposition
was the judge looking at the,
prospect of success under 221(a) or
was he looking at it under another
So the Crown submission is that
the standard of review would apply to both.
As either (a) or (b), and so in this case...
No, but it's not a question of standard of review,
the question is Messieur advanced that
you cannot look at evidence
I'm not sure that it's right,
without evidence, that was the point
So no evidence is required to a uphold
Justice Gleeson's decision
that the Amendments have no Prospect of success.
He was entitled to look at the the pleadings
on their face the proposed amendments
without getting into any evidence beyond that
and that was your position before.
Yes
reading the pleadings per se.
It was enough to come a "no reasonable
prospect on the cause of action" to strike
Yes
It was like a 221(1)(a)
Yes.
Okay
And then, with respect to the
second appeal for summary judgement
the test of course is set very clearly
that Justice Gleason was to consider
the test being in Hryniak and Maildin
that case also sets out the
standard of review for this court,
an appellate review, at the
first level or the second level
In fact, it deals with the appellate review
at the Supreme Court level.
The Crown submission is that that same standard
applies in this court in dealing with motion for
summary judgment where
the Federal Court deals with it
by a judge, rather than
a prothonotary at first instance
What I don't understand in your motion is,
first you make it under 221
You agree that 221 is a motion to strike.
Yes
215 is the Rule for the summary judgement, so, and
frankly, I have some difficulty and
that's why I'm raising it just speaking
for myself at this stage and we
haven't decided anything but
I have some difficulty with the argument.
that you cannot have an Action
that would include different parts
and the whole pupose, if it were true
that you have to have 135 on its own
Then, I don't see under what authority one
would strike, completely kill the other parts,
rather than remove them and
separate them as different Action.
There you would have to you know,
maybe bring a motion to strike under 221.
Either because no reasonable cause
or prejudice and whatever,
if you want to have evidence, but you can't do
I just can't understand why you say
"I'm going to strike other claims"
just because you feel that 135 should be on its own.
It's like substance over... form over substance.
The Crown did bring a motion to strike and
that was dismissed by Prothonotary Milczynski,
she suggested that a motion for summary
judgement might be more appropriate.
And your motion to strike was in
respect to which portion of the action?
Again, related to the question of law,
it simply boiled down to
whether the conduct at issue could be resolved by
determining whether the coins are "goods" or not.
But how can that be determinative
of the other claims included?
Because that is the only conduct
that was at issue in the Plaintiff's claim
Let's have a look and explain it to us, because
I don't see it when I read the Statement of Claim.
Of course. The claim can be framed
however a plaintiff wishes and
it can be very expansive particularly
where the plaintiff is acting in person.
but nonetheless the only issue that
the Federal Court will consider
is the question of, in this case,
whether the coins are "goods"
and Justice Gleeson was very clear
about that point, that section...
the Customs Act provides a
very limited review in this...
It's not really an ordinary action at all.
It's a statutory appeal by way of Action
You're changing course here.
key to
this would be the key question
to all the claims because
my question to you is not whether you
can put them in the same proceeding,
which is procedural. Okay?
What courts do when things are put
together, that should not be put together,
we separate them
They don't just strike it.
Unless there is no merit, but you have to
have a motion looking at the merit
of the other stuff.
If you're saying to me and that's
what I heard that this one question
was determinative of all of the other claims,
that's a different story
but I couldn't see it when I read it
When I read the Statement of Claim,
it was not evident to me
maybe just because I didn't see it, you know.
you can say that
That one question. Are they "goods"?
Is enough to determine the
merits of all the other claims?
I take your point, but obviously
Justice Gleeson felt differently,
and the Crown supports his position.
But that's why we're a Court of Appeal!
Okay, so that he thinks
differently is another story
and the Crown submits that the only
issue that required any review whatsoever,
whether it's by summary judgment or at a trial,
of the Plaintiff's claim was whether
the coins are "goods"
I assume that you tried to convince him of that.
So now is your time to try convince us
But that's the point here
if the coins are not "goods", then
clearly the defendant loses the case. Full stop.
and if the coins are "goods"
What else is available to my friend
under a statutory appeal if this is not an Action
You would lose what case?
You would lose the case for punitive damages,
you would lose the case for Declaration
that the Minister of Public Safety has a policy
aiding crime and terrorism in Canada,
what would you be losing?
I think it's fair to say that
Justice Gleeson felt that there was
no prospect of success for those claims.
There may not have been a specific motion
before him at the time to strike those claims,
but a motion had as I said in brought
previously to strike and had been dismissed.
So that's not very good for you.
what I mean is that it's not a judge
looking at a claim without a motion.
because there is another party.
We have an adversarial, so somebody,
In this case, Mr.
Mr Hociung has the right to present
his argument as to whether to be struck.
Yes. So
you can't start from there
If the court disagrees with Justice Gleeson
that those ancillary claims should not
have been struck, then,
if you if you follow through
on that proposition, then you can make a
determination on the motion for
summary judgement whether the coins are "goods",
and allow the rest of the claims to proceed
and send it back to Federal Court
and rest assured my client will move to strike.
Okay, but you see my point. You just ...
We're a court of law.
You can't say "Ok, we're going to take shortcuts
because we don't want people to spend
money for nothing". We just can't do that.
I take your point
and here, it may well be that you're right
but I just can't see how you can strike
other claims without even looking at their merit
okay, and your argument about
135, you see my point.
If you had struck or sought under
106 to separate those
then you'd be fine, but I don't see how you ...
I just and I'm not talking for my
colleague, just me, so convinced me.
you know, if you think you can,
but procedure. He has a 135
Yes,
he has a write of action. Maybe for damages
and for whatnot. Maybe he's wrong.
Maybe he's gonna lose, he has no case, or whatever.
but we can't just say because put them
in the same Statement of Claim
[unintelligible] ...they would be time barred
Well, for sure, for a case whether the
ruled that the coins are "goods",
it's difficult to conceive that he would
have a claim for punitive damages
Because he hasn't alleged that he was
mistreated in any way by border officers
Then you'll have an easy job on the motion to strike
Yes.
Okay. Now, have you considered,
and do you have something
[unintelligible] I'm in a bind because
I don't know the case at this stage
is the Crown under 3(1)(b)
from your understanding is
vicariously responsible for fraud
For [unintelligible] outside of their duty
So that would be easy for you to produce cases.
And Messieur has until June 6
June 7th
June 7th, so many days do you need to
as many as you [unintelligible],
but I don't need much time.
So an extra two days because you'll start
looking now, of course, so by the 9th,
yes.
so that is done...
and you realize that
and I'm raising this for both sides
if we were to say that the rest has to go back
there may be a jurisdiction problem
and a time limitation problem.
Time limitation if it is within 106,
and if it is not within 106
you can still have a cause of action
against the officer, but if that is so,
this court has no jurisdiction.
I'm just raising this so you know.
that when we send it back, there may be
a lot more hurdle under other than
reasonable cause of action on its face just
because of the wording in the
time limitation and whatnot.
Yes.
Okay, you're all following on that.
I am. Yes,
okay.
Okay. Now you want to say anything
else about the Amendments or are you
102, Mr Hociung raised a lot of error
Yes
You made a statement that the ancilliary
thing should not have been struck
Can you show me where they were struck?
They weren't stuck. It's just that ...
We usually make a comment that it should not
have been struck. Couldn't find where it actually
So in fact, no, that's correct, your Honour.
They were not actually struck.
He simply decided the issue about
whether the coins are "goods"
and then of course... so whether
the coins are are "currency" and
subject to his findings, he decided
to dismiss the entire action.
with he didn't strike it
he dismissed the action
You realize how it becomes very important.
Yes, you would have to find
that the ruling on coins as
"goods" and "currency" was determinative
of all the claims in the plaintiff's claim.
or that procedure form
Yes.
override the substance and you can just dismiss
because you happen to put it on
in the same Statement of Claim
Yes.
So, in the Federal Court, the Crown took
the position that the coins are "goods",
Justice Gleeson found that they are
both "goods" and "currency"
and on appeal to this Court, the Crown is
happy to support Justice Gleeson's
ruling on both those points.
The Crown referred to several pieces of
legislation before Justice Gleeson
The Crown repeats those submissions,
but in addition the Crown is relying
on the Customs Tariff which I cited in the
memorandum, as well as two cases decided under the
federal Export and Import Permits Act.
Both are fairly old cases, but they made their
But we'll look through that... just a second.
In my own mind the first one I would like
you to clarify if you can is the proposition that
if something there's no tax to be paid,
it doesn't need to be declared unless
there's an obligation to declare
under another Act
Right.
Can you start with that?
That it's absolutely false; if a good exceeds
the limit allowed for perfect goods purchased
abroad during the trip to be declared it must be
Absolutely must be reported. Even if no tax
is to be paid on it in terms of custom duties
because there may be GST
Okay. So where do we have that
provision that says "if you exceed you..."
you're talking about the $800 for 48 hours
Yes, that's all it is.
Where do we have that provision?
So you're looking for the specific
provision in the Customs Act
yes, because you say that what he says is false
easy to find it
so I reproduced provisions of the
Customs act that the end of my
memorandum, but those
particular Provisions would
out in the regulations, which
as you
not believe I have reproduced in full.
So I would have to provide that
to you subsequently.
We have the Custom Tariff,
Yes.
[unintelligible]
no
because you do realize that that
was one of his main arguments.
throughout
so it's a bit surprising that
it's not in the material
Well, it's a bit of a surprising argument milady.
It's just because there is no duty owing
a good doesn't have to be reported.
For example, let's take it
the keys out of this case.
If the goods are currency if their value
is an excess of 10,000 dollars
It's Proceeds.
Yes, they have to be reported
but there's no tax upon those.
Yes, but I think what Messieur
said, he completed this when we asked about fruit
there could be a series of other legislation
that would impose a duty to declare
and that would be administered by the Customs
so
We need something tangible other
than it makes no it's false. So.
I thought that that argument was raised in the
Apellant's memorandum
It is, but I mean, are you asking for
the citation to the regulation that
Yes, I want a piece of
[unintelligible] or something or
Do you have a case?
There's no case.
Ok, there's no case, then
something other than your word?
What I could do, what I can offer to the court, is
when the time comes for me to send in
the case law on the fraud of a public servant
I can provide as well to reference to the
specific provision in the regulation
that deals with the specific limits.
We don't want to extend this overly,
so if you could provide that within...
... until, before the next Wedesday which is the
time that Messieur is coming back from wherever,
then he can answer about this in his letter
that provides the answer for
3(1)(b) of the Crown Liability
fraud cover or not, you follow me?
The second section will be whatever you have to say
about the regulation that is being raised in the
This is not a memorandum. Okay, all
this must not be more than five pages.
all this.
Ok... very well.
But to apply that...
I just want that to be put in the minutes
The 29th
Perfect.
You need to put that into a context
you say in your view, everything that is over
the limit must be declared, whether or not
there is taxation
... but how can it be over the limit
if there is no tax on it?
Because he.. the plaintiff paid, and this is
uncontradicted in the evidence, USD $2700, for
these ... USD $5700 for these coins when in fact
that represented 29.5 times their face value.
So
So there's an obligation to disclose it
just because it was over his exemption
whether or not there was tax on it.
OK. And are you going to address your
interpretation of those
provisions that you push us through?
Yes.
Unless you have any further questions.
Those are all my submissions.
I asked you whether you're gonna take us
through those provisions, and you said "Yes"
Which.. so the provisions that you asked
about, the regulations, the limits.
no, no... He said section 11 of the Currency
he went through... several errors,
such as not considering section 11
of the Currency Act
and [unintelligible] that exempts
foreign and whatnot
well milady I have I mean I can take you through
Justice Gleeson's decision and detail,
but the Supreme Court of Canada
has said that, you know, the
The appellate Court does not need to
conduct the same analysis that
was conducted by the Federal Court.
Sorry. This is a question of law.
Yes
Question of law.
Okay. So are we clear that on
question of law is correctness?
Yes.
Okay, so why are not are we
not conducting it ourselves?
So his question was that Justice Gleeson is...
Argument is that Justice Gleeson did not
consider section 11 of the Currency Act
just because that particular section is not
referred to expressly in Justice Gleeson's
decision doesn't mean that that
legislation was cited to him. Act was before him.
he str... Justice Gleeson referred to numerous
pieces of legislation in his decision
dealing with currency.
Do you agree with Justice Gleeson's
statement in paragraph 53
that I would have thought would be
point of interest for the Crown,
at the sentence the one that mentions Customs
instead of Proceeds, but if you go
"the denominational or face value of the
non-circulation coins would have to be declared"
So let's say you had a drug
smuggler and decides to bring back his
100,000 and buys $1 bills that are worth ... you'd
be happy that he doesn't have to declare that?
Yes, because he has to declare it as
"goods". It's not money laundering. It's...
if you bring the Flowing Hair dollar coin,
which I refer to in my memorandum,
there's a picture of it at the back
of my book of authorities.
If you bought that and brought it into Canada,
you would have to declare it as a "good"
because you purchased it, well,
the last time it was bought,
it was bought for 10 million dollars US.
You don't have to declare it under the
Proceeds of Crime and Money Laundering Act
because the face value is less
than 10,000 dollars Canadian.
You declare it only as a good.
The Proceeds Act only comes into play
if the face value of the money that may
or may not be laundered is over 10,000 dollars.
And what about if that's right, then
you can put to the bank or in your...
I'm just I'm just puzzled by the fact that
you don't think that people have to declare.
... the million dollar they bring in
it's just because it's on face value.
The money laundering provisions of the
Proceeds of Crime Act do not apply
to collectible coins that have a very low
face value but a very high fair market value.
It's like bringing in diamonds. The Proceeds Act
just doesn't apply in terms of money laundering
even though a drug smuggler or a terrorist can
bring one diamond in, and it's
easily over 10,000 dollars. It's different
legislation that applies to catch that.
The  Act only applies to the
importation of actual currency and only...
[unintelligible] ... face value
... [unintelligible]
I would have to check but I believe so.
Why don't you check!
You mean it's not in our authority
Well, no.
We have a judgment that is based
on that and we don't have ...
We have the provision that is at
issue whether but we don't have
we don't have the entire act before
the court in my book of authorities
And yeah, but
we have the specific provision.
So the reporting that... if we look in the Act, and
search "face value", we should
find a disposition about that
Of course!
Okay, so I'll... we'll find it.
But it is understood by the Border Service
Officers that they are to go by that,
the face value of currency.
not the fair market value
... it's conceivable that you could have old
Canadian dollar bills that are worth much more
than one dollar right now, but still would not be
within the 10,000 dollar limit. Would not be over.
They don't have to be declared.
Because of their face value but if the terrorist
goes to sell it, you know and obtains more than
10,000 dollars. Obviously. That's a problem.
so you have no problem with that, ok
So essentially you're saying you ..
[unintelligible] over the judgement in respect
of the Declaration for "goods" and money
And you rely on your written submission?
Yes.
Well look... in terms of the question you asked me
"did the Justice Gleeson consider section 11
of the Currency Act" to take one of
my friend's arguments.
At paragraph 50 of Justice Gleeson's reasons
for decision he devotes almost a pagePer
and a half of his reasons for decision to
citing Section 8, for example, of the Customs Act.
I simply want to raise the point again that
he simply because he hasn't specifically
cited section 11 doesn't mean
he didn't consider it
Okay, and it's clear that
the argument wasn't important.
Yes.
Now, paragraph 65
Messieur said that contrary to what
was stated by the judge there,
he did argue that at paragraph 9 of his
material on page 118 of the motion
so is there something wrong in this
Uhh.. No.
I don't think I'm following you.
Paragraph 65 to judge says "the plaintiff has not
argued that the coins, if found to be goods, are
exempt" The appellant says that's
wrong, he did argue
Do you know whether that's...
Oh, I see what your point is. It's not the finding,
it's whether or not Messieur made... yes.
Yes, Justice Gleeson is absolutely
accurate on that point.
I would have to take you to his notice, I'm sorry,
his written representations filed in response
to the motion for summary judgment.
So let's look at 118, it says it's on page 118
Plaintiff reponse to the motion...
Again, it's a problem with my
book on page 118 is not
doesn't have paragraph, it's tab numbers
At page 118 of the appeal book
Appeal book, 102-18
paragraph 9
I think you're saying it should
be it should be page 121.
Okay,can you look at your book
and it may be one page 1.1
paragraph 9, it starts with paragraph 24
Find the paragraph 9 to which you refer and
show it to the registrar officer so we'll find it.
it is very very difficult to follow
when the books are not organized
yes, it's on page 121 of our book
Anyway I think we've got your point,
the point being made that this argument
was put to the judge
Whether or not the judge accepted as if
an issue exactly yes. Yes, that's the point
and you don't have nine and tell us if you
think it's the same argument that they've got 65
because maybe it's not the same argument.
Well, the plaintiff has ... admitted.
The evidence is clear
He paid 5700 US for the coins. So clearly that if the
coins are "goods", that would trigger
the reporting requirements.
Ok, 65... "the plaintiff has not argued that the
coins, if found to be goods, are exempt from the
reporting requirement set out in 12(1)"
12(1) of the Customs act
So what do we have at 9
But now we're talking about the different Act.
In nine we're talking about the Excise Tax Act
section 12(1) of the Customs Act.
All goods that are imported shall except in such
circumstances  subject that may be prescribed
be reported to the nearest
So all goods that are imported.
Yes, so
you're saying that argument?
I'm saying that argument must have been made
to the judge because the plaintiff conceeded
that he paid an amount in excess
of the allowable limit not to report
so maybe the Judge misspoke when
he says the argument has not been made.
It's possible, but I don't see
that anything turns on that
Okay, it's just that we need you to guide us.
Yes
You're kinda saying,
"Ok, you [unintelligible] all this"
Fair enough. But Milady, I didn't anticipate that
the plaintiff ws going to take issue with
something on this with respect to this
particular sentence in Justice Gleeson's reason
He didn't make that point in his memorandum.
Okay, so that point is not in the memorandum.
and it's not
Okay, I don't see anything turning on it.
Okay. The next point was a paragraph 68.
The reference to the fact that there are
overlapping provisions in itself shows that the
matter is not sufficiently clear
for the judge to decide.
The Crown disagrees. Just the mere fact that
they're is an overlap does not mean that
there's a conflict and what Justice Gleeson did
was review all of the different pieces of relevant
legislation very clearly and craft together
the clear proposition that goods...
that goods... these collector coins are "goods"
There was no easy answer for him.
There was no definition of money
in any of these Acts, but by looking at all of
the piece of legislation, which he has carefully
sited at length in his long decision.
He found as a fact that coins are "goods".
Yeah, that's a matter of law.
Yes.
There is no issue.. we all know what
"goods" are, there is no disagreement
Okay, the next point that was raised and
the Appellant argues that this question alone
was not enough, and the judge had also to consider
whether the decision under appeal was otherwise
In fact the only task before the Federal Court on
the motion for summary judgement was to determine
whether the coins were
"goods" or "currency" or both.
The outcome of that determination was
determinate of the entire statutory appeal.
There was no need to allow any
of the other claims to proceed.
And Justice Gleeson so found.
Okay, but..
And the ministerial decision to be clear was not
technically something he judicially reviewed
This is a statutory appeal by way of action.
So Justice Gleeson technically did not need
to consider the ministerial decision beyond
its actual outcome.
because it's "de novo"
yes.
With different evidence
Yes.
Okay.
We've pretty much conceeded that the
in an action on different part,
the argument about 81.23(a)
in the Excise Tax Act shows that if you want
to preclude many claims in one you have to say it
so you're not talking about this
no,
okay.
We do understand that
Whatever the merits you have to go by the rules,
absolutely.
Okay, I think.
We're talking when you type of the goods that had to
be reported you say the goods that had to be
reported were in excess of your exemption
I thought you said refers to goods in excess
your personal limitation, personal exemption.
Yes, that's true, but here the
goods were clearly in excess
yes, it's a matter of law. The only time he has to
report goods is over, I believe it's $800 Canadian
So if you are out of the country for 7 days,
and bring back $500 worth of goods,
First you can say to the officer
that "No, I'm not bringing back any"
Yes... No, that "I am not bringing
back anything that I have to declare"
You have to disclose that he's bought goods,
but they are not subject to the reporting
requirements under the Customs Act,
or the Proceeds Act.
Let's say instead of buying at $5000,
he bought it at $500
and his exemption was 800,
he would not have had to declare
No.
but I have nothing to declare"
He could not simply say
"I have not purchased any goods abroad"
Because of the form that says
"did you bring any goods over the limit"
On the form? Yes, but if you're actually asked
- this was a land crossing -
if you're asked by the Border Services officers
squarely "Have you purchased anything abroad",
technically, you should say
"I haven't purchased anything over that limit"
Beyond that...
When you look at section 12(1), Customs Act,
it seems to suggest that
"all goods must be reported to the nearest..."
Only over the s... da... da..
There are exemptions
That's where you have it in the
I will provide those specific sections
exemptions to section 12
and we all have those exemptions when we
travel abroad, typically for alcohol
everybody knows that
So the main provision in fact for the duty to
declare is 12(1), but some exemptions
and that's regardless of whether or not
you're obliged to pay taxes
because those exemptions did not apply to the
plaintiff, I did not put them in my authorities
but I will provide them
Were you seeking costs
If my client is successful in this Court, my client
will ask for costs on the appeals, but success
was divided in the court below, but it would only be
with respect to the appeals, and
my client would be happy that
If we were to agree on the question of law, money or goods, but disagree that you could dismiss the whole action.
Then it will be, you wouldn't be seeking costs.
I would have to conceed that
success would be divided
And in the first instance, you did say
each party bear their own costs.
Yes.
Success was clearly divided before Justice.
Thank you.
Reply is just about what to say.
However there my friend made quite a few
actually responded but quite a few points.
I'd like to start with 101 the amendment
He noted the Teva jurisprudence. Teva was relied
on in Hryniak in order to derive the principles
under which an amendment
may be struck. Hryniak was
you can't... this is in your memorandum in chief
it is in your authorities. That's not a reply
a reply is something that was new in what he said
otherwise you have to say it all in the first part
he said that
Teva gives the judge the authority to strike the
the amendment
to refuse the amendment. Yes, and you've
already told us about the jurisprudence.
Yes, however, Teva would not apply
why it wouldn't apply
Teva would not apply because it was guidance
for summary judgment motions.
Not for amendment motions.
Perfect next.
my friend said
That the plaintiff did not alege mistreatment,
which is not correct. One of those specific claims
is against officer Debski for threats
threats of violence
Okay. perfect.
The respondent also made submissions about time limitations for officers or and your Honor made a point about the hurdles.
of having time limitations fortunately, in this case the timers of limitations have not even started
what do you mean
the timers have not started
the individuals are still expecting this ransom payment for the return of the money. So that means that the
fraud is continuing. It's not a finished transaction.
ok, so... ok
that was not the judge didn't determined anything.
No, that was a point. So
you don't need to reply. I'm just I think we were discussing what you need to face later down the road if we return it.
And about the daily section exemptions, there's fun and mix the arc the daily that respond makes the argument that some of the exemptions that come under schedule 3 of the exact Tax Act do apply which are the exemptions with respect to time spent outside the 800 dollars per day.
Yes. Yeah. He's going to give us, but he said that well, if the authoritative...
12 of the Customs Act is the operative provision and that there are some exceptions with respect to time of travel
my point my reply is that the same exemptions or the exemptions that that he refers to come from the same place as the exemption for coin they all come from schedule 3. So the point is if there is an exemption for time spent outside of Canada.
This would be equally for all the other
You'll be able to put that in your letter when... that's the part 2 of your letter, remember?
He is going to give us the regulation and you're gonna have ... so that's going to be easy to reply
very well.
the respondent also stated that he wouldn't he would be happy that a smuggler would declare a large sum of
gold coins as goods and this
however, he said
I believe he said that depending on the amount of gold coins, they would have to be reported. However, the drive of the respondent is that no amount
that there is no amount of
no prescribed amount for gold coins
we're just we're not talking about the Custom Act
Under the Proceeds Act, no amount of gold coins would have to be reported.
No, he said they would have to be if they're over 10,000
so that's one section and then he didn't say they would have to be reported on the Custom Act
On the contrary, he said they would have to be reported if purchased.
He contradicts
himself by saying that there is a limit and for the proceeds act.
The CBSA and as shown in the evidence before the judge. There's a memo about precious metals where coins such as these and other financial instruments that are gold bars for example are not to be reported.
Okay, we cannot exist in the appeal book.
You are referring to the Precious Metals Bullion and Coin Information Bulletin?
Yes
So I've got it in the very first...
and what is the contradiction
The contradiction is that that internal memo, which is a secret document
says that
currency gold and silver precious metals
but it has to be before the..
You've got it in the appeal book with respect to the amendment, part of the same action
So it's just in a different appeal.
It is in both, Your Honour.
Okay, and that would be too I was actually document. So what is it that you're saying is a contradiction of what he said
so that internal memo instructs CBSA officers
where
So you let us read this and it's contrary to what he is saying, is that what you're saying?
your page 100 of the appeal book, which is the second page of the memo.
second page of the memo
not in our book, but second page of the memo, yeah
the second page of the memo, under tariff classification
coins are also to be treated as goods and not as currency and the word "not' is underlined
The last sentence of that of that paragraph says "across border currency and monetary instrument report", which is formed
But I don't see how ... this is a tariff classification, what does that have to do with the proceeds
Because it instructs the last sentence instructs officers. "Do not require reporting under the monetary instrument regulations."
a cross border currency monetary report is not required
to be filed by the importer at this time
and that is without regard to the amount.
This document you got ... in discovery?
So I would give one minute after you're done for an answer from the other side because normally these things that are already raised by you have to be raised all in the first time around.
I'm sorry, that's high pressure that I would like under.
Yes. Pretty good. Okay. So with the next Point
next point that the Respondent makes is that
that declaring financial instruments and gold currency under the Customs Act would be sufficient reporting. Even if the amount is large such as terrorist or smuggler. The problem is that the
The two reporting regimes address different needs. The Proceeds Act reports go to the FINTRAC organization, which is able to track and find patterns and financial movement. Whereas Customs Act reports only go to Industry Canada tabulations to find out generally how our economy is doing
So a report pursuant Customs Act would be would go under the radar of the FINTRAC
And they will not be able to
To find ...
But it has really not much application to your case
Your case,
I believe I believe this is exactly what the CBSA is trying to do
No, because you're under 10,000.
It doesn't apply to my case
No, it's what I'm saying.
It doesn't apply to my four coins, but my claim that is
next point.
No, he said that you made the argument
so the judge knew about it, he just didn't feel that it was necessary to write it in his reasons
my reply is that section 11 would have been determinative, and his conclusion would have been different
About the conflict.
Where judge Gleeson
the respondent says that there isn't an actual conflict. However it paragraph 72 of the decision judge Gleeson says there's no real conflict.
And that implies that there is a conflict is just not to be seen as real.
Yeah.
Your Honour with respect to the de novo treatment of the of the case, the de novo treatment applies to the action as a whole which means that every every claim in the action has to be considered de novo.
It doesn't mean that
the rest of the action was never...
It's the first time. De novo - first time
Yes. However, it doesn't mean that the
The appeal is respect to section 135 needs to be determined de novo and even if it did if the judge had a lot of 135 from the beginning there was no evidence before him whatsoever of any contravention? There was no evidence of what was or was not important.
next
there's all I have on
and am I correct that it was not disputed that you did not declare those coins
Correct
It's not descriptive that they were coins.
What they were, what their face value was and what their purchase value was.
In the narative report of officer Debski, which is the officer that did the search and the finding that he noted at the very end that he understands that the coins are technically currency, but
he needs to treat him as "goods" because of this memo. That instructed him.
I want to commend you on your knowledge of your file and the judgement and everything, you've done extremely well
do you have anything to say about the costs?
I would like yes, I do. Of course. Yes.
You're not a lawyer, so you can't get costs except disbursments and things like that
Well Your Honor in the motion to strike at the responded mate earlier in the case, Prothonotary Milczynski found that even though I'm not a lawyer, I'm still entitled to time.
Ok, but do you want an ammount?
It's difficult ...
Make the submission together with the others? I need to check my paperwork.
and when you do that you have to put evidence so the other side can
respond
very heavy-handed and vexatious. I like to point out that
before you do this things the judge didn't find anything vexatious or anything.
No, I'm making point about costs on the appeal.
Yes, but we haven't seen anything that says before
I would like to submit the letter that the respondent submitted to the registry with respect to the appellants submission of
of the memoranda. He lied in the letter to the registry claiming that the service was done improperly.
So far in this case the Respondent has fight in every way possible to slow down and to make it more expensive to
it's already in the registry in the file, so we don't need to fi..., but there is no ... whether it was right or not...
We'll consider your appeal, but it takes a lot to say that ... fraudulent or vexatious...
If you allow me the time to explain
No.. no more time.
You didn't ask for it in your memorandum
in my memorandum
that's supposed to include everything about costs
In that case, I suppose normal costs
You will put your disbursment and the time you spent in the letter, and we'll be able to answer
Now thank you very much
I'll give you a minute to answer the page of bulletin that Cross Border Report is not required.
Sure. That bulletin predated Justice Gleeson's ruling. It was obtained during the discovery process prior to the summary judgement motion, so obviously that bulletin would have to be updated with respect to the treatment of currency.
Was it before the judge or not?
I don't believe so.
Okay, so if it not before the judge
Why would it be in the appeal book?
Because, well because appellant has put several documents that were in avail... produced in discovery into the book
You're supposed to object to that. He's not supposed to add things which were not before the judge.
yes, milady he...
I did ask for a specific ruling that we'd be allowed to file separate books of authorities just as an example and that was granted. It was Justice Renny. There's a history in this file of not being able to agree on what documents should go into which books
So on the question of that bulletin you're saying was not before Justice Gleeson when he was making the decision on amending the Statement of Claim
because that whole bulletin, I think, is part of the reason why he wanted
Yes
So do you know for sure whether or not the judge had that in front of him?
It wasn't part of the evidence that the plaintiff submitted for his motion to Amendment the Claim.
To the extent that the bulletin
Is it part of the evidence?
That would have been an affidavit for the motion to strike.
That's not the same.
What we're looking at is what was on the record for the summary judgment motion and the motion to amend
They were different affidavits filed for both.
So this would not have been
You know what... you check your files
Check your files, I want an exact thing on this in your letter, the same letter that you have to write
The point to take away though was that the bulletin would have to be corrected, given Justice Gleeson's ruling on currency.
Right the whole point here. Is that the bulletin seems to imply that the Border Services officers are not to treat collector coins as currency.
And Justice Gleeson in effect changed the law. He said it's both coins and curency.
Okay.
So what you're saying is that...
This may have been an internal administrative... view
yes.
but if it's not one that is in sync with the findings of Justice Gleeson
Yes, and it predates Justice Gleeson's ruling
And that's why I want to make sure that... and that would be the sentence is in paragraph 53 that we discussed
Yes.
because
we may decide not to discuss this matter
of course
and that
okay, so I understand here.
Hearing it, whether it was before Justice Gleeson on the two motions that are on appeal before us is very important.
So thank you very much. We will take this on the reserve. He's
order
sitting is now concluded.